Guide to the Jacob Lofman Papers TAM.285
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jacob Lofman Papers
1928-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Horowitz, Helen
Lofman, Jacob
TAM.285
1.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 manuscript box.
Jacob Lofman (1911-2002) was a Polish-born photojournalist who maintained a lifelong interest in Jewish history and culture, and was involved with organizations devoted to Socialist Zionism and various forms of socialism. His photographic work appeared in many mass-market magazines, and was distributed for many years by the agency, PIX, Inc. The collection consists of personal and political correspondence, reports, newsletters, bulletins, memorial programs, flyers, and drafts of articles. A few items, mostly correspondence, relate to his work as a photographer.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Helen Horowitz in 2002. The accession number associated with this gift is 2002.017.
Arrangement
Organized into one series: 1. General Files, 1928-1998. Files are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Jacob Lofman (1911-2002) was a Polish-born photojournalist who maintained a lifelong interest in Jewish history and culture, and was involved with organizations devoted to Socialist Zionism and various forms of socialism (including, for some years, Trotskyism). His photographic work appeared in many mass-market magazines, and was distributed for many years by the agency, PIX, Inc.
He was born on August 31, 1911 in Poland and apparently joined the Socialist Zionist organization, Hashomer Hatzair at an early age. He continued his membership in the group in the U.S. and wrote for its New York-based publication, Hashomer Hatzair. After emigrating to the United States he became a professional photographer; his work was widely distributed through the agency PIX, Inc. Among the many celebrities he photographed were Robert Frost and Sugar Ray Robinson, and one of his photographs was included in the historic "Family of Man" Exhibit at the Museum of Modern Art in 1955. He and his wife, Rivke, had no children.
He read widely in Jewish culture and socialist politics, in several languages, and was associated with a number of socialist groups and parties in the U.S. He was a follower of Max Shachtman by the late 1930s and was a member of Shachtman's Workers Party in the 40s; he resigned from the Party, following a dispute with Shachtman, ca. 1948. He became involved with the Socialist Party in the 1950s, with Michael Harrington's Democratic Socialists of America in the 1960s and 70s, and eventually with Social Democrats, USA. He continued to read widely in left political literature, was a speaker on left and Jewish themes, and wrote for a number of newspapers, journals and newsletters over the years.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of personal and political correspondence; reports, newsletters, bulletins, memorial programs and flyers relating to the many left-wing organizations that Lofman was associated with, or interested in; some drafts of articles and translations that were sent to him by friends, or sent for his editorial attention; and a few items, mostly correspondence, related to his work as a photographer. Included are a few translations of articles by Polish dissidents, and some correspondence and printed items relating to left-wing politics in Israel.
Photographers -- United States.; Socialism -- United States -- 20th century.; Socialist Zionism.; Trotskyism -- United States.; Horowitz, Helen; Social Democrats, U.S.A.; Democratic Socialists of America; Workers Party (1940-1949); Socialist Workers Party; McKinney, Ernest Rice, 1886-1984; PIX, Inc.; Lofman, Jacob
- General Files, 1928-1998
  - AFL-CIO: Tom Kahn Mailings, undated; 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appeal Bulletin (James T. Burnett), No. 12-13, Jun 1985-Nov 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appeal to Reason Bulletin (James T. Burnett), No. 5-6, Jun-Sep 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appeal to Reason Bulletin (James T. Burnett), No. 9, Sep 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appeal to Reason (James T. Burnett): Correspondence, 1989; 1993-1994; 1996; undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Appeal to Reason Newsletter (James T. Burnett), Vol. I, No. 1-7, Feb-Aug 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Appeal to Reason Newsletter (James T. Burnett), Vol. II, No. 4-5, Apr-May 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Appeal to Reason Newsletter (James T. Burnett), Vol. II, No. 9-10, Oct-Nov 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Articles: Labor, general, 1959; undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Articles: Left Politics, general, 1968-1985; 1996; undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - B'nai B'rith Bugle (Lake Success Lodge and Chapter), Vol. 6, No. 7, Mar 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - B'nai B'rith: Lofman Talk, [1974?] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brown, Irving: "Alternatives to Wars of Attrition: The Role of Democratic Forces in a Political Solution" (National Information Strategy Center), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bulletin (Albert Gates, et al.), Apr 12, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Bulletin (George Marlen and J. C. Hunter; published by Red Star Press), Mar 1943 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bulletin [includes J. R. Johnson], Apr 1943 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bulletin on the National Question (Albert Gates, et al.), undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bulletin on the Negro Question (David Coolidge), undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Business Cards (Jacob Lofman), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Committee in Support of Solidarity, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence, Outgoing, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee/Democratic Socialists of America, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee/Democratic Socialists of America, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Democratic Socialists of America: New York, 1991; 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Falk, Julius: Leninism, the Comintern and Putschism (pamphlet), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Fourth Internationalist Tendency, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Frost, Robert: Publishers Correspondence re: Lofman Photos of, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Furmansky, Moshe (Hashomer Hatzair): Memorial Tribute, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Glotzer, Albert: Biographical Sketches (Martin Abern, Albert Goldman, and Ernest Rice McKinney), undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Glotzer, Albert: Letter to Jacob Lofman, Jun 14, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Hashomer Hatzair issue includes "Toward a Greater Zionism" by Yaakov Lofman, Oct 1935 (Box 1, Folder 60a)
  - Institute for Democratic Socialism, 1990-1995 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - International Socialist League, undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Jews for Peace and Equality, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Kahn, Tom: Obituary (Washington Post), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Labor Solidarity Network of Greater New York, 1987; undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - League for Industrial Democracy, 1970; undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Lofman, Helen: Funeral, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - MAPAM: Meir Yaari, "Theses toward the Third Convention of MAPAM", 1957 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - MAPAM: Peretz Merchav and Yosef Shatil Statements, [c. 1957?] (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - McKinney, Ernest Rice: 90th Birthday and Memorial, 1976; 1984 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Memorial Gatherings: Michael Harrington and Sidney Hook, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Milstein, Tom: "Contemporary Threats to the Open Society" (typescript copy), undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Notes (in Hebrew), undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - PIX, inc.: Sale of, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Passover Haggadah, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - The Real World (Marathon Group), No. 6 (Tom Milstein, et al.), May 1979 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Revolutionary Communist Party, USA, [early 1980s] (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - School Notebooks (Jacob Lofman, in Yiddish and Polish), 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Sedova, Natalia: Statement for Radio Liberation (recorded in Mexico), [1956?] (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Shachtman, Max: Statements about (Gordon Haskell, Albert Glotzer, Mordecai Povzea, and unsigned), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Social Democrats of New York, 1981; 1985; undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Social Democrats, USA, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Social Democrats, USA, undated (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Socialist Party/Young People's Socialist League, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, 1970-1972; undated (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation Convention, Dec 1972 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Socialist Workers Party, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Socialist Workers Party, Jan 1940 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Socialist Workers Party, Feb 1940 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Socialist Workers Party, Mar 1940 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Socialist Workers Party, Apr 1940; undated (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Solidarity/Against the Current, 1990; undated (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Tool and Die Makers Lodge 113, International Association of Machinists: House Un-American Activities Committee Hearing (Memorandum and Albert Dency Testimony), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Translation from Hebrew: Yosef Barzilai, "Jerusalem, August 1929", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Translations from Polish: Andrzej Stawar, "Glosses: The Break", undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Translations from Polish: Interviews with Jacek Kuron, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Translations from Polish: Irena Born, "The Rehabilitation of the K. P. P.", 1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Translations from Polish: Rajmund Habermass, "The Mole's Disaster - K. P. P.", undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - The Trotsky School of Falsification, Part One (Red Star Press), 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Warsaw Ghetto Uprising Commemorations, Metropolitan Synagogue, 1989; 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Workers Party, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Workers Party, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Workers Party: Bulletin, No. 6, Jan 1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Workers Party: Bulletin, No. 8, Apr 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Workers Party: Bulletin, No. 9, May 1941 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Workers Party: Bulletin, No. 10: Convention Discussion, Aug 1941 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Workers Party: Bulletin, No. 11: Convention Discussion, Sep 1941 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Workers Party: Educational Bulletin, Jul 1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Workers Party: Information Bulletin, No. 9, Jun 12, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Workers Party: Supplement to Information Bulletin No. 8, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Workers Party: Internal Bulletin, No. 3-5, Aug-Nov 1940 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Workers Party: National Educational Bulletin, No. 1, Nov 1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Workers Party: New York Local, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Workers Party: New York Local, City Convention Bulletin, 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Workers Party: Trotsky Memorial Meeting, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Yale Socialist Notes (with letter from Phil Dauman), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Young Social Democrats, 1982; 1984; undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Youth Committee for Peace and Democracy in the Middle East, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Clippings (mostly Yiddish) I, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Clippings (mostly Yiddish) II, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)